[Music]
foreign
back to another episode with it's Dr Dan
and today we're going to be looking at
more introductory biochemistry we're
going to be learning how to go from
fissure projections to Hayworth
projections so whenever we have a
Fischer projection the entire idea
behind this was a show chirality of a
molecule so whenever we represented uh
different intersections with crosses you
this would tell you that oh we have a
chiral Center to the molecule so for
this particular one I have d-mannos you
can see that there are four chiral
centers on this one but the whole idea
about this is to transform it into a
three-dimensional structure in a ring
projection so we have to cyclize this so
the whole idea is whenever we do any of
these we have to first start by
numbering our carbon chain so we always
give the the highest priority functional
group which is our aldehyde or aldose
and this case
so Aldos because that has an aldehyde on
top
and that has the number one and we'll
number all of our carbons
so when we go through this the first
step is that you need to rotate your
structure now the point of rotating this
so when we're rotating it clockwise 90
degrees it helps us see where all the
different OHS and the CHS in this
structure are going to be oriented so
the first part of this is that we will
have our C double bonded o
notice how when I started this I had it
pointing to the right at the very
beginning and now it's pointing down I
purposely like to do that because it
helps remind us that all of the OHS that
are pointing down are going to be the
bottom of our ring structure and
everything else is going to be the top
so we're going to copy everything down
we're going to also renumber it too to
help us keep track so we have one two
three four five and then number six we
will write in
so we will copy over our lower so it's h
h o h
and then o h and then we will put in our
last ch2oh
and then it's always the opposite on top
so there's always a hydrogen opposite of
every o h so it's always a quick way to
remember you always have a pair of each
of them
now when we do this we have to figure
out how the reaction is going to occur
so if you remember from my previous
video on on hemiacetals acetals and
things like that whenever we go through
these structures the big idea is that
the aldehyde or the Ketone is going to
be reacting with an alcohol
however if you kind of look at the
structure there are five different
alcohols on it so which one do you pick
well let's try to take a look at it so
what if we so let's try to draw this as
a ring structure and what we'll do is
we'll try to illustrate it showing the
let's say the last alcohol reacting and
see how that turns out so when we draw
these the first thing you're going to do
is you're going to put that c double
bond o on the right hand side and what
this is going to do is going to turn
into an alcohol eventually
so we're going to then start drawing as
a ring structure so we'll have the
second position second carbon third
carbon
fourth carbon
the fifth carbon and then our sixth one
go into our ch2 o h
now when we have the structure here the
couple of things that we're going to do
we're going to draw the bottom of it
with a wedge notation this helps show
the three-dimensional shape behind it
then we're going to capture all of the
top and bottom parts of the molecule so
when I say top and bottom the parts in
blue here are going to be bottom
and then the parts in
we'll say yellow are going to be the top
so when we do these so one thing you're
going to see is I have an o h pointing
up and oh pointing up
and oh pointing down
and then an o h pointing down and why
don't we just kind of color code those
for ourselves to see which ones were top
and then we had in blue which ones are
pointing down so that's kind of matching
where those were on that ring structure
and we will also number it as well so
that we can see what's going on so yeah
one two three four five six now if this
were to form this way
it's going to cause an exchange of all
the different parts right so the alcohol
group turns into an ether and then the
aldehyde turns into a alcohol so kind of
the put it simply whenever we see these
so how is the reaction occurring
so if you remember from my previous
video
we would always have the following
reaction would take place
so the
o would react with a c on and the H on
each part this thing would rotate as a
result
and when that happens we're going to be
making a ether
that's one of our structures
as well with an alcohol so that's going
to be part of it now based on this
current look here
the way that this would form is that
oxygen is going to become a part of the
Ring
so when this happens we would have one
two three four five six seven members of
the Ring seven member rings are
extremely unstable
so it's not going to be this one that's
going to be participating
so a quick way to remember for how to
know how many parts of a ring they're
going to be it's always going to be
either a six member ring
for out typically for aldehydes so it's
not all the time but probably 99 of
examples that you're going to see in
Biochemistry is going to be six member
with an aldehyde and the other one is a
five member ring being that these are
the most stable ring structures that we
can find in Biochemistry so how can we
count it so there's a quick way to do it
so if we go back to our original
structure
the the alcohol is going to react is
going to be your last you go to your
last chiral carbon and let's make um
let's make that a little bit smaller
one second
so we go to our last chiral carbon which
is right here
so with that one here I made a little
too small
we'll go to the last chiral carbon and
what we're going to look at is the
alcohol on that carbon so we look at the
last cross
and this is going to be a the alcohol
that's going to be participating the
reaction so this will be our sixth
member how do I know it's six is it
starts at the aldehyde it goes to the
next carbon third carbon fourth carbon
so this is like our unofficial numbering
we start at the C double bond o
then we work our way down the structure
counting one at a time to see how many
ring members we have so it's going to be
six so let's redraw this structure
um with six so we'll come down to this
we'll come down to the next page we'll
copy and paste our
structure that we drew earlier
so we have it
so we paste that down here and now what
we're going to be doing is creating a
six member ring so we start with C
double bond o have one two three four
five
and then as we were I was mentioning
before well being that this had the
ch2oh pointing to the right what's
actually going to be happening here
is this entire structure is going to end
up rotating so it's going to rotate
around so when that rotates it's going
to allow for the o h bond to be pointing
at
that uh
the C the C double bond o so I'm going
to draw that in purple for us and then
when that rotates depending on your
original geometry or original projection
of your fissure projection
the ch2oh can either point up or down so
how do you know where that's going to
point
if it was a d projection at the
beginning the cah2oh is op
if it was L the ch2oh
is down so that's a really important
thing to write down for yourself for
later and we'll show that again in the
summary so this is one of our little
important little tidbits for ourselves
okay so that's pointing up okay so we'll
like kind of highlight that in blue to
represent that step now what's going to
happen is the reaction is going to take
place that I had before
so this entire ring structure is going
to go through a reaction
where it's going to we're going to break
two bonds and form two bonds
as a result so I'm not filling in any of
the groups yet just showing what the
reaction is
and when that occurs we're going to have
our basic shape
meaning that when this happens we will
have the ether form in the ring
and we're going to have an alcohol form
outside of it so if you remember this is
our Hemi acetal
now when that occurs this allows for two
possible rings to form
either we can have and that all depends
on this carbon right here in red now
what this this carbon has a very
specific name
this is the Anna Merrick carbon and what
happens is that there's two types that
can exist
it's either going to form
this structure on top or where the o h
can point down like that I have here so
both of these are possible and I don't
mean erase all that but that's okay
now these exist in equilibrium with each
other so
we will talk about the two types in a
second
so we fill in our ch2oh from earlier
they're both pointing up
we then bold in our line structure
just to illustrate that 3D look because
remember this ring is slightly bent so
it's not a flat ring it does have a
three-dimensional shape
now we're going to fill in our blue and
yellows from before so if you remember
yellow is pointing up so we had the
first two were or we had the first two
were up
and the third one was down
we'll do the same thing over here oh up
oh up
oh down and let's color code that for
ourselves
so we have yellow yellow
and then the blue was down just to help
us see that so that is our structure now
let's go back to the anomeric carbon so
anomeric carbons help tell you one more
letter so whether it's a beta
or if it's Alpha and what that has to do
with is the following lines so if I
highlight these in blue again
like so
so if we have it where both lines are
pointing together meaning CIS so the
same then it's referred to as beta
meaning if the ch2oh is up and the o h
is up then it's beta if they're both
pointing down
then it's also beta
with Alpha that's referring to trans so
if we have a ch2h pointing up
and then an o h pointing down then that
would be trans or the opposite of that
so if you have ch2oh pointing down or oh
down so these are up up
down down
or
so you can that backwards so
up
Up Up and Down
down
let's separate that for ourselves this
is up down
and down up
okay so that is how you draw your
Hayworth projection for Manus in this
case so if we were going to name both of
these we could this one would be beta D
mannose and that's how you can tell if
it's beta if you're ever giving a name
and you need to and it gives you a beta
Alpha you have to draw the Hayworth
projection and then this would be Alpha
D minus so these are animers of each
other they both exist in equilibrium so
the beta tends to be about 63 percent in
existence and the alpha is 37 in nature
it's a very odd percentage with the two
so I kind of summed up this a little bit
so bear with me for one second of how to
draw them so I put a little guide
together so the first thing you're going
to do is on the how-to guide is you're
going to always write the Fischer
projection
then you're going to determine how many
members are in your ring structure
remember it's gonna be five or six so
you start on the C double bond o h
and then you're going to go to the last
chiral oh so counting along just like
how we did with highlighting
if it was l or D that's going to tell
you where the ch2oh is so how we can use
this guide so first you want to
determine six member is going to be a
hexagon
five members going to be a house and I
made a I'm going to make a video doing a
five member example it's going to be a
little shorter to show that
so you can see both styles
so that would be a five member ring
then if it was L that's going to be
pointing down on your ring structure
if it's D the ch2oh is going to be
pointing up on your structure
now when you turn everything 90 degrees
like how we did earlier
that's what's going to allow you to show
the top and bottom OHS in your structure
it helps you see it a little quicker
eventually you'll get you'll know that
like the right side of the Fischer
projections down the left side is up but
I think for most students who are new or
not planning to be chemists it doesn't
hurt the redraw it's also good practice
for yourself too
Alpha
it is always trans so when this when the
ch2h and Alpha and the oh are opposite
of each other so the way to think about
opposite is if you look at the alpha
symbol notice how it crosses so it's all
about opposite sides
um so beta is the same the way to
remember that is that the B the like the
loops of the B are on the same side it
kind of helps so you'll see the ch2oh
and the oh are the same on both of these
structures okay
so the easiest way to do these if you
remember both of the shapes so six and
five all biochemical structures in a
ring projection are going to be these
ones unless you have a teacher trying to
assign really crazy projections but most
of the time you're going to see one of
these so if you can remember those two
shapes you don't have to know the
mechanism behind the reaction you can
just copy down that shape and then
connect them if you have to do a
disaccharide or polysaccharide but this
is how to do a Aldos a worth projection
from a fissure I hope this video helped
and I hope to see you next time for
future introductory organic and
biochemistry videos see you next time
this is Dr Dan and please hit that like
And subscribe button to help support the
channel alright I'll see you all next
time bye
foreign